Guide to the Diva Sanjur papers, 1967-2002.
Sanjur, Diva papers, 1967-2002.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Diva Sanjur papers. 1967-2002.
29-2-3252
Diva Sanjur
3.1 cubic ft.
Correspondence, publications, academic materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes course material, correspondence, publications and proposals, relating to Diva Sanjur's career in the Division of Nutritional Sciences.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Emeritus professor in the Division of Nutritional Sciences.
Diva Sanjur received a B.S. in 1958 from the University of Puerto Rico. She earned a M.P.H. degree from the University of California-Berkeley in 1962 and a Ph.D. in nutrition at Cornell in 1968. Between periods of graduate study, she worked as a nutritionist in the Department of Health in Panama. Sanjur joined the Cornell faculty in 1968 and remained a member of the faculty until her retirement in December 1999. She also held appointments as an ad hoc professor at the University of Puerto Rico and at the Research Center for Food and Development in Hermosillo, Mexico.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes course material, correspondence, publications and proposals, relating to Diva Sanjur's career in the Division of Nutritional Sciences and her research on cultural factors in the Hispanic community that affect dietary preferences and the socio-economic variables associated with infection with intestinal parasites.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sanjur, Diva; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Nutrition--Research.; Parasites.; Nutrition--Diet.; Hispanic Americans--Nutrition.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Collection closed for processing.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Course Materials
Box 1- Folders 1-9
A. Nutritional Science Course # 245
Box 1- Folders 10-33
B. Nutritional Science Course # 631
Box 1- Folders 34-60
C. Nutritional Science Course # 325
Box 2- Folders 1-12
Box 2 - Folders 13-23
Series II. Symposiums and International Work
Box 2 - Folders 24-52
Series III. Proposals
Box 2 - Folders 53-60
Series IV. Cornell Programs
Box 3 - Folders 1-3
Series V. Book Material
Box 3 - Folders 4-16
Series VI. Correspondence
Box 3 - Folders 17-30
Series VII. Publications
Box 3 - Folders 31-53 and two binders
Box 4
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Course Materials
  - Card - Watercolor of Uris Library, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Artwork, cards (Box 1)
  - Overheads - Household Economics and Nutrition (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Overheads - Measuring Dietary Change Among Migrant Populations (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Overheads - Behavior and Self Efficiency (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Overheads - Changes in Diet and Consequences, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Overheads, Food Habits (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lecture - Parasitic Infection and Malnutrition, 1991-11-15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture - Hispanic Women and Nutrition, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lecture, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Overheads - Diet Counseling and Instruments of Change (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NS 245
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Overheads (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Overheads (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - First prelim and key, 1997-10-09 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Overheads (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lecture notes (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Material (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Lecture Materials (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Diet risk factors/ chronic diseases (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Women, nutrition, and health (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Demographic perspectives on food and populations (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Demography/ food supply - socioeconomic status, 1991-11-04 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Overheads - international nutrition (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Prelim and course materials, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Criteria for grading, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hunger and Food Insecurity (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Overheads and class notes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Poverty overheads and notes (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Food security and nutritional surveillance, Pelletier, 1991-11-22 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Prelim and lecture notes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Overheads and class notes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Course material (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Prelims and course materials (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - NS 631
    - Course materials (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Lab #1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lab #2 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lab #2, Fall 1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Lab #3 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Lab #4 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Lab #4 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Lab #5 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Lab #7 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Block's Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Readings (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Sample menu - 24-hour recall method (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Sample questionnaires (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Thickness Indicator (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Exam materials (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Exams (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Dietary Assessment Methods (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Transparencies (originals) (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Extra handouts (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Course outline (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Food choices - slides and outlines (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Prelims and assignments (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Dietary Assessment Methods (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Overheads - Diet Assessment (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Course material (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Diet History Form (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Food Cost Study (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - NS 325
    - Food cost study - Sociocultural Aspects of Food and Nutrition, handout (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Discussion Period (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Discussion Period - Measuring Food Intake: Data Collection (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Methods for Collecting Data at the Family and Household Level (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - LCR, Bibliographies, 1988-11-11 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Food and Culture in America (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Panel discussion handouts - Preschooler Nutrition (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Panel discussion handouts - Overweight and Obesity Issues (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Panel discussion handouts - Diet and Cancer (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Panel discussion handouts - Teenage Nutrition (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Panel discussion handouts - National/ International Trends in Breastfeeding (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Panel discussion handouts - Anorexia Nervosa and Bulimia (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous - correspondence JS (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous - Hatch Funds (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Taren: Food Frequency Diet Assessment (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Food habits (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Three-Day Food Record (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous - Diet Assessment (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Interviewing for the Facts (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dietary Data Collection, 1991-10-23 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Course material - demography/ food supply (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Student paper - "Family Influences on Nutrient Intake Among Rural Dominican Women", 1988-12 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Written by M.Mort
  - Student paper - "Effect of U.S. Immigration on Dietary Changes", 1985-12 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Written by J. Tiffany
- Series II. Symposiums and International Work
  - W.O. Atwater Symposium, lab assessment, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - EFNEP Presentation, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Mexico (CIAD), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mexico, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Korean Lecture - emails, journal articles, and abstract (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Barcelona, Spain (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Cuba material (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Santo Domingo/ Dominican Republic - Plan Sierra (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Universidad de Puerto Rico, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Puerto Rico material (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Penang Meeting - pamphlets, brochures, booklets, articles, 1988-02 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Penang Meeting - reprints and papers (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Penang, Malaysia Meeting- photograph, 1988-02 (Box 2)
  - Penang, Malaysia Meeting - photograph, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Dominican Republic Workshop, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Panama Project - questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Panama Project - list of children who received ketrax treatment in Nata and Rio Hato, Alicia C. Garcia, 1988-06 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Crompton - Panama Project (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - D.W. T. Crompton, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - FASEB meetings - Ascariasis - International Nutrition Seminar (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - FASEB meetings, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - FASEB meetings - Rosemeire Turumoto, 1990-04-01-1990-04-05 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - FASEB meetings, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Brooklyn slides (draft) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - HASP committee - caracas, Nov. 1994 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Human Ecology Forum Editorial Board - International Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - McIntosh Book (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Dominican Republic- CIIFAD (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Letters to D.S. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Culture specific teaching (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Series III. Proposals
  - Dr. Pilar Parra - Project Proposal, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Grant Proposal - Monitoring Food Consumption of Low- Income Households in Venezuela, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Proposal for CSRS Project (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Grant proposals, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Proposal for CSRS Project (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Grant proposal - Dr. Walraven's Correspondence (Hatch Project) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Grant proposal - New York Sea Grant Institute (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Student - Doctoral Thesis and Research Proposal, Diva Sanjur - Chair - CSRS Proposal, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Series IV. Cornell Programs
  - International Nutrition Program, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hispanic Studies Program (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photos - nutrition (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series V. Book Materials
  - Book contract (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Book correspondence (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book - Hispanic Food and Nutrition - originals (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Book chapter - Dr. Sanjur (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Book material - completion schedule (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Book material - Mexican - Americans (ch. 3) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Book material - Dietary Compliance (ch. 9) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Book material - Puerto Rican Diets (ch. 4) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Academy for Educational Development (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Book Reviews (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photos (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Journal of Nutritional Education - Manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series VI. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence to Dr. Sanjur - permissions, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Guaymi Study - correspondence, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Emma Perez's letter, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Maria Teresa Oyarzun letter, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Human subjects correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Mieko Kagaya - Visiting Fellow, DNS, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with Winna T. Rivera, re. trip to Puerto Rico, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Memos, correspondence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Susanna Tsai - correspondence (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Salvador Villapando - correspondence (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Personal correspondence (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series VII. Publications by Sanjur
  - "Sociocultural Aspects of Nutrition - A Cornell Slide Set" (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Food Habits of Low - Income Children in Northern New York", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Nutritional Anthropometry", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Validating the 24-Hour Recall Method as a Dietary Survey Tool", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Food Behavior and Related Factors of Puerto Rican - American Teenagers", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "Use of Path Analysis as a Statistical Technique for the Analysis of Qualitative Nutritional Data", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Nutrition Intervention and Sociocultural Determinants, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "The Dietary Status of Preschool Children: An Ecological Approach", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - "The Effect of Environmental Changes on Food Consumption and Nutrient Intake Among Puerto Rican Families", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - "Food Preferences - Their Conceptualization and Relationship to Consumption", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Food Consumption Surveys: Issues Concerning the Processes of Data Collection and Data Analysis, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Assessing Food Consumption: Selected Issues in Data Collection and Analysis, 1997 (Box 4)
  - "Nutritional Consequences of U.S. Migration Patterns Among Puerto Rican Women", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Salud y Nutricion de los Indios Guaymi: Panama, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Contributions of Ascariasis to Poor Nutritional Status in Children from Chiriqui Province, Republic of Panama", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "Nutritional Aspects of Ascariasis", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Written by Sanjur, Compton and Nesheim
  - "Contemporary Diet and Body Weight of Navajo Women Receiving Food Assistance", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - "Intestinal Helminthiases in Relation to the Socioeconomic Environment of Panamanian Children", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "Parasitic Infection and Malnutrition in Developing Countries", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Written by Sanjur and Nesheim
  - "Dietary Patterns and Nutrient Intakes of Toddlers from Low-Income Families in Denver, Colorado", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - "Dietary Patterns, Nutrient Intakes, and Nutritional Anthropemetry of Urban Puerto Rican Toddlers", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Report - "A Community Program to Empower Indonesian Villages to Improve Their Nutrition and Health", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Paper - "The Impact of Urbanization and Female Employment on Nutrition in Colombian Households" (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Articles by Sanjur, 1967-1984 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Articles by Sanjur, 1986-1999 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Memories from Diva Sanjur Nesheim (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Spanish recipes and nutrition teaching materials, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Booklet: "Mexican American Food Practices, Customs, and Holidays" from "Ethnic and Regional Food Practices, a Series" (Box 3)
  - Binder: "Puerto Rican Food Habits: A Socio-Cultural Approach" (Box 3)
  - Binder: "Food Purchasing Patterns: Food Expenditures and Nutrient Profiles Among New York State EFNEP Households" (Box 3)